now we need to talk about what is true
hormone optimization versus what is
testosterone therapy six years ago I
have been on certain physiological
levels of free and total testosterone
since 2017 and um then we started
immediately for myself on DH and
Pregnant alone as well but then I
learned the T from Dave Lee that's why I
think of it and he says not to start
just like that without having any
symptoms so the burning question for me
was to ask you again okay well that's
where Dave and I we're going to do a
video on this too I do believe because
we need to Circle back on that yeah uh
okay now we need to talk about what is
true hormone optimization versus what is
testosterone therapy now Dave after we
talked last time it we came to the
conclusion that we're treating we're
talking about two different populations
of men he's treating men and their are
talking about men in their 20s early 30s
me and you are middle-age and older men
it's a what is hormone optimization
hormone optimization is preventing that
age related decline in hormones so I'm
going to disagree with Dave on DHEA PR
all those things I've got all the
studies on each one of those as well but
when we're treating middle-aged and
older men understand that all hormones
have beneficial
effects okay they work synergistically
but each hormone has beneficial effects
the goals of what we do are to maximize
The Beneficial effects of each hormone
by optimizing levels
that's what hormone optimization is it's
about preventing any age- related
disease disability dependence or Frailty
it's not waiting until we get a disorder
or a disease before we start treating
it's not waiting until we get symptoms
of a deficiency before we start
supplementing the problem for those
younger men is that they cannot discern
between feel-good effects and beneficial
effects now before we talk about this
with regard to pregnant loan or DHE and
those things let's understand this let's
set some ground rules here Stephen can
you take Tylenol not a trick question
can you take Tylenol for a headache
bother you to take Tylenol I I I've I've
never taken it really well have you ever
T well tell me something that you've
taken over the counter just for a
headache or cold ibuprofen okay so you
can take Ibuprofen right so can I so
when we talk about what we're about to
say we're speaking to the masses that
have no problem taking a dose of
ibuprofen or two or whatever for for
inflammation or whatever we may have
going on we're not going to speak to
those guys because there's always that
guy that's going to you know speak up
and say oh I can't take us I got this
we're talking about the
99% of people that can take it we're not
referring to you guys that are that 1%
outlier that can't even take Tylenol or
iprof and the majority of all of us can
either take Tylenol or IPR without any
problems but there's going to be some
people that's say I can't take Tylenol
because I get a headache so we're
talking about the majority of people all
right so hormones that exert the most
feel-good effects the two that have the
greatest impact on how we feel function
perform and our overall health are going
to be testosterone and thyroid I can
literally base my adjustments on
symptomatic Improvement not necessarily
levels of course we follow levels those
are your two really Feelgood hormones
the other hormones like vitamin D DHEA
pregnant they don't have significant
feel good effects yes sir that's going
about to make a comment out there that
well I feel it when I I'm not talking
about you we're talking about the
majority of people that take it there's
not significant feel-good effects from
it all right but we take it for its
beneficial effects all right that's why
we're that's why we're raising levels
and once again we're talking about
treating middle-age and older men with
hormones not guys in their teens and
early 30s necessarily remember
testosterone therapy is just that
testosterone therapy guy in his teens
20s early 30s probably fine just getting
along with just testosterone therapy but
for middleaged and older men it becomes
about hormone
optimization because we don't want to
wait till we get symptoms of a
deficiency of DHE or anything else who
want to prevent the deficiency this is
about
prevention not just about treating when
you get sick so we don't want to fall
into that trap don't take preg nalone
Steve until you get aici of preg nalone
Steve don't take don't take DHE until
you feel bad because you don't have
enough DHA prevent that from occurring
so like DHE it can stimulate your immune
system improve memory it can increase
energy has anti-cancer properties it can
improve mood and help with depression it
can reduce your cardiovascular Risk by
decreasing viscal body fat and therefore
lower hypertension cholesterol in some
men it reduces insulin requirements
protects against osteoporosis improves
erectile dysfunction protects against
muscle atrophy and protects against
inflammation in fact it's used to treat
lupus which you know they used it for
Lupus the goal is the better the levels
to better the benefits and the goal of
all of what we do is to maximize The
Beneficial effect of each and every
hormone at middle age and older we're
not talking about Dave Lee's crowd of
guys in their teens and 20s maybe early
30s we're talking about us older guys
we're maximizing The Beneficial effects
and balancing between avoiding any
unwanted side effects that's all it is
just a simple Balancing Act and it's
just some people could take more DHEA
than others pregnant alone testosterone
thyroid all of that so that's really
what this is about is I am about hormone
optimization for middle-aged men and
women as they age for preventive
purposes okay it's about the so the
younger crowd has a little bit different
you know mentality and it's a little bit
different treatment of course they're
not suffering necessarily from signs of
a all their hormones deficient at this
point in time but whenever you do treat
a middle-aged and older man with these
hormones very few of them have any
so-called side effects okay very few
most side effect get for DHE is going to
be acne that we see in men and women
just lower the dose to the dose they
could tolerate happens with me I have to
take a lower dose you know than I than I
wish I could but still nonetheless I do
supplement with it so I just wanted to
you know Dave Le is right about his
crowd that that he and he's first first
as is he and I were talking that look
that's I treat guys that are in their
20s and you know maybe or 30s and you're
treating these older people that's right
and another mistake that is made out
there is that many men don't really
understand that symptoms of low thyroid
are almost identical to those of low
testosterone many areas so many men that
are out there are getting treated with
testosterone still feel no better in
certain areas well it's because they're
throwing testosterone is actually a
thyroid problem or a thyroid problem as
well so that's why we optimize them all
that's why we're treating for
symptomatic Improvement so I'm glad you
brought that question up yeah Dave does
a great job on all those but but he's
not he's not talking about the
population of men that that that I
predominantly treat and that's a totally
different population of men sure I agree
and um I'm still taking the pregnant
alone and the DHA we we started you on
that a long time ago so good for you
good for you never changed the winning
team good good good good well see I mean
it's just about sometimes the devil's in
the details and so Dave and I like I
said think he's put out good content but
I think that I was going to tell Dave
next I'm thought Dave you need to make
sure you you you be very speciic look
I'm this is the crowd that I'm really
talking about because when we look at
the studies where we're using pregnant
alone and DHEA and and older men and
women we don't have the problems that
he's reporting that these younger men
have okay we we don't see that okay all
right ke that was some excellent
information thank you so much for doing
this again you're welcome buddy I hope
you got what you needed out of it sure
thing we'll Circle back around with
estra dial of course and like I said I
one of my interest in my practice is of
course prostate cancer why because I'm
at highrisk for it for family history so
take it very seriously uh I have many
men that I treat that that have prostate
cancer have been treated for for
prostate cancer so the history of uh
testost prostate cancer is fascinating
men all men should know about it and
understand why they were deprived for
decades
unnecessarily okay let viewers know how
to contact you if they want to reach out
tier1 hw.com so that's all you need to
do tier1 hw.com okay I'll put the link
in the description thank you so much D
you got it man thank you
Stephen